Guide to the Michael Lally Papers MSS.361
Fales Library and Special Collections
Michael Lally Papers
1930-ongoing
1975-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
Lally, Michael
Granary Books (Firm)
MSS.361
55 Linear Feet in 88 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 3 flat boxes, 2 custom flat boxes, 4 oversize flat boxes, 2 record cartons, and 3 flat-file folders
10 Gigabytes in 94 computer files
85 audiocassettes
11 sound cassettes (dat)
9 videocassettes (u-matic)
47 videocassettes (vhs)
1 videocassettes (video 8)
1 videocassettes (betacam)
1 websites in 1 archived website
The Michael Lally Papers represent and document the life and work of New Jersey-born poet, screenwriter, small press publisher, and actor Michael Lally. The collection includes correspondence, screenplays, manuscripts, poems, drafts of articles, publicity, analog and digital audiovisual recordings of poetry readings and acting work samples, digital photographs, acting scripts, journals, calendars, scrapbooks, clippings, books, small press publications, address books, and posters, all dating from the 1950s to 2012, with the bulk of the material from the 1970s to the 2000s. An archived version of Lally's blog, http://lallysalley.blogspot.com/ which contains Lally's reviews and comments on movies, television shows, literature can also be found in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of Acting Contracts files located in Series II.B., Box 100.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Granary Books, Inc., 2012. The accession number associate with this purchase is 2012.361.
In 2019, http://lallysalley.blogspot.com/ was added to the web archive through the use of Archive-it. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession number associated with this website is 2019.071.
Appraisal
Eight computer discs were deaccessioned after forensic imaging and analysis determined items contained no usable data or were duplicate material.
Movie titles existing in NYU's holdings were removed from the collection including Drugstore Cowboy, Ramona, Pump Up the Volume, White Fang, Basic Instinct, The Rapture, and Cool World.
A duplicate audiocassette for the JazzSpeak album was deaccessioned, while the CD copy was retained.
Publications and books that existed already in NYU's holdings. Duplicates of publications, books, and other print material were removed from the collection.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to fales.library@nyu.edu
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series, all of which have been further separated into subseries. The series and subseries arrangement of the papers is as follows:
Series I. Writings, Publishing, and Related Projects
Subseries I.A. Work Files
Subseries I.B. Publications
Subseries I.C. Readings and Events
Subseries I.D. Literary Correspondence
Subseries I.E. Publishing Correspondence
Series II. Screenwriting, Plays, and Acting
Subseries II.A. Screenplays, Plays, and Related
Subseries II.B. Acting and Voice Over Work
Subseries II.C. Correspondence
Series III. Personal
Subseries III.A. General
Subseries III.B. Correspondence
Biographical Note
Michael Lally (1942- ) was born and raised in New Jersey. He joined the Air Force in 1962 and after four years left the service. Through the G.I. Bill he received his undergraduate and graduate degrees from the University of Iowa. In 1969, he moved to Washington, D.C. to teach at Trinity College. While in D.C. he became involved in the local poetry scene, where he established the Mass Transit poetry reading series which was considered an important incubator for Language Poetry, and launched a poetry publishing collective, Some of Us Press (SOUP) with wife Lee Lally, Ed Cox, and Tina Darragh. SOUP published Lally's book, The South Orange Sonnets, in 1972. In 1975 Lally separated from his first wife, the poet Lee Lally, and moved to New York, where he wrote poetry; founded a small publishing company, O Press; and also edited the anthology None of the Above: New Poets of the USA.
In 1982 Lally moved to Los Angeles to pursue opportunities in film and television as a writer and actor. He appeared in numerous movies, television episodes, and plays including Basic Instinct, White Fang, Father Dowling Mysteries, and Deadwood. In addition to writing his own original screenplays and plays, Lally was a script doctor in which he contributed to existing screenplays. During his time in Los Angeles, Lally co-founded the Poetry in Motion series (1988–1996), which received media attention for its mix of Hollywood celebrities and poets. While living in California Lally also helped found and edit the original Venice magazine.
Lally has published over 27 books of poetry and memoirs. His awards include the 92nd St. Y Poetry Center's Discovery Award for The South Orange Sonnets; numerous National Endowment for the Arts grants; and the 2000 American Book Award for It's Not Nostalgia. In 2006, Lally started the blog "Lally's Alley" (http://lallysalley.blogspot.com/) in which, as of 2019, he continues to write daily reflections on his personal life, movies, politics, and poetry. As of 2019, he is living and working in New Jersey.
Custodial History
In 2012, the material was collected by Granary Books during two visits to Michael Lally's home in Maplewood, New Jersey. Much of the material had been preliminarily sorted and organized by Michael Lally. The collection was transported to Granary Books in New York City where portions were refoldered and rearranged.
In circa 2012-2013, the material was purchased by the Fales Library & Special Collections and transferred to NYU.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Electronic Records Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The Michael Lally Papers contains material on both Lally's professional and personal life. This material includes a significant collection of correspondence specifically related to Lally's involvement with the L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E poets during their formative years, with small publishers, and with people in the poetry communities in Iowa City, Washington, D.C., and New York City during the 1970s through the 2000s. Lally's writing files include his manuscripts and drafts for poetry books and articles, as well as working files on his publishing companies, O Press and Some of Us Press (SOUP). A mix of paper and electronic files relate to his poetry readings through posters, publicity, and images from events. Small press publications and alternative journals in this collection contain many of Lally's writings, dating from the late 1960s through the 1990s, reflecting the output of poetry and literary communities during this time. Acting scripts, movie and play posters, publicity, and analog and digital audiovisual material represent Lally's work as an actor and screenwriter in Los Angeles during the 1980s through the 2000s. Personal journals, scrapbooks, calendars, address books, school yearbooks and papers, digital photographs, and correspondence with family and friends date from the 1950s to the 2000s.
An archived version of Lally's blog, http://lallysalley.blogspot.com/ where, as of 2019, he writes daily reflections on matters ranging from his personal life, movies, and politics to poetry. The blog was first captured in June 2019.
Separated Materials
Two DVDs were transferred to Avery Fisher in July 2019: TV Show: Big Apple (Lally acted in) and Short Film: Being Born
Poets, American -- Correspondence.; Personal correspondence.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Small presses -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Serial publications.; Calendars.; Scrapbooks.; Acting.; Television scripts; Screenplays; Screenwriters.; American poetry -- 20th century -- Periodicals; Plays (performed works); Hollywood (Los Angeles, Calif.); American poetry -- New York (State) -- New York; Poets, American -- New Jersey; Artists and community -- United States; Granary Books (Firm); Lally, Michael; Blagg, Max; Cooper, Dennis, 1953-; DiPalma, Ray; Dlugos, Tim; Winch, Terence
- Series I. Writings, Publishing, and Related Projects, 1961-2012, undated; 30 Linear Feet in 53 manuscript boxes, 3 flat boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 record carton, and 2 flat-file folders; 7 Gigabytes in 27 computer files; 68 audiocassettes; 4 videocassettes (vhs)
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into five subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Work Files
  Subseries I.B. Publications
  Subseries I.C. Readings and Events
  Subseries I.D. Literary Correspondence
  Subseries I.E. Publishing Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains electronic and paper material related to Lally's work as an editor, poet, and freelance writer during the 1960s to 2000s, including writing and editing work files; publications containing Lally's work; video and audio recordings of readings and spoken albums; event publicity; correspondence with his literary colleagues; and correspondence with small publishers regarding his projects.
  - Subseries I.A. Work Files, 1961-2012; 11 Linear Feet in 19 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 1 oversize flat box
    Material is arranged beginning with published work titles in alphabetical order, followed by the remaining files on his work kept in their original order.
    This subseries contains Lally's writing files for published and unpublished works, notecards tracking his published works (1960s to 2009), and files related to his publishing ventures, O Press and Some of Us Press (SOUP). His work files on individual pieces and books typically contain notes, manuscripts, contracts, proofs, publicity, and correspondence, including files for The South Orange Sonnets, Catch My Breath, It Takes One to Know One, and It's Not Nostalgia. These work files also contain larger editing projects, including his work on the anthology None of the Above: New Poets of the USA which included works by L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E poets Ron Silliman, Bruce Andrews, and Ray DiPalma; New York School poets Alice Notley and Joe Brainard; and poets working outside any community association such as Patti Smith. Files containing unpublished loose poems are in this subseries, as well as chronological poetry manuscript books dating from the 1950s through the 1980s, his journals with writing ideas, and Lally's reviews of others' work. This subseries contains files on his first published piece Markings on the Wall including rejection slips, manuscript, and correspondence from the 1960s. Files with his unpublished biographies Loose Canon and Poor Moth Boy in the Moon are in this subseries. Lally's editorial work is also represented through his Franklin Library files and Venice Magazine files, which include photographs by musician Andy Summers.
    - Attitude, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Can't Be Wrong, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
    - Catch My Breath, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10-13, Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Charisma, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3-9)
    - Guess Who, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hollywood Magic, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - It Takes One to Know One, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13-17, Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - It's Not Nostalgia, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4-16, Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Just Let Me Do It, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Late Sleepers, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - The Lines Are Drawn, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Malenkov Takes Over, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - March 18, 2003, circa 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - Markings on the Wall, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
    - Master of Ceremonies, undated (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Mentally, He's a Sick Man, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - My Life, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - None of the Above, circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 18-22, Box 5, Folder 1-7)
    - Of, 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 8-14)
    - On the Back of His Head, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
    - Oomaloom, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Que Pasa Baby?, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Rocky Dies Yellow, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - The South Orange Sonnets, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
    - Stupid Rabbits, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - What Whithers, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - What You Find There, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Publishing Record Notecards, circa 1960-2009 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Loose Poems, 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 17-19, Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    - Eileen [Devlin] Funeral Poem, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Merrill at 60 Book, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - O Press, 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Some of Us Press (SOUP), 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Venice Magazine Art and Photographs, circa 1988-1995 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Assorted Meeting Minutes, Notes, 1978-2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Complimentary Lists, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Contracts and Agreements, 1976-2012 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Tables of Content, Dedications, and Acknowledgements, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Poetry Manuscript Books, 1950s-1986 (Box 8, Folder 8-10, Box 9, Folder 1-6, Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Poetry, 1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - MCMLXVI Poem, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Proud Cut, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Loose Writing Notes, 1992-1993, undated (Box 10, Folder 8-10, Box 11, Folder 1)
    - May 28th 1942, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Stories / "Fiction", 1961, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Assorted Notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Lists, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Untitled Notebook of Children's Poems, 1970s-1980s (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Unpublished Chapbooks and Art books, undated (Box 38, Folder 4-9)
    - Unpublished Stories and Essays -- Iowa Fiction, 1965-1974 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Pretentious Writings, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Mother Monday, circa 1964-1966 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Unpublished Manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - The Fucking Enemy Shows Up, 1970s (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Old Poetry Manuscript Wayne Clifford Never Published, circa 1967 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Re Bops, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Getting What We Want, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Satisfaction, circa 1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Throwing Eagles, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Kid's Book, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Red White Black and Blue, circa 1976 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Unpublished or Incomplete Manuscripts, 1960s-1970s (Box 12, Folder 9-11)
    - Narrowback -- DC, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - The XYZ Reading, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - DuPont Circle, 1974, undated (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
    - Novel for Scribner's, 1970, undated (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
    - Unpublished Autobiography -- Loose Canon, circa 1995 (Box 13, Folder 7-9)
    - Unpublished Autobiography -- Poor Moth Boy in the Moon, undated (Box 37, Folder 32, Box 38, Folder 1-3)
    - Assorted Writings, 1975-1982 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Flyers and Covers by Michael Lally, 1971-1974 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Autobiographical Writings, 1971-1979 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Political Essays and Reviews, 1960s-1970s (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Under the Tea Newspaper Column, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Gender and Sexuality, undated (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
    - Music, Book, and Movie Reviews, 1970, 1977, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Blurbs for Others, 1977, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Blah Blah Blah, 1960s-1970s (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Adventures in Poetry, 1971-1974 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Alternate Currents, 1980s (Box 14, Folder 12-14)
    - Angel Hair Press, circa 1973 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Assorted Poetry Reviews and Essays, 1970s (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Ted Berrigan, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Ralph Dickey, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Short Pants and Marilyn Mailer, undated (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Lynn Dreyer, undated (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Publishing Correspondence, 1969-2006 (Box 37, Folder 29-31)
    - Full Court Press, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Jack's Book, circa 1978 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Poetry Project Review, undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Poetry and Book Reviews, 1970s (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Reflections on Poetry, circa 1973 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Review -- A Place at the Table, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Reviews -- Recollections of Gran Apachería and Turtle Island, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Reviews -- Seeking Air and The Manner of Music, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Review -- Terrance Winch, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Review -- Tropicalism, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Review -- Underrated and / or Overlooked, undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Review -- White Niggers I've Known, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - The Franklin Library, 1977-1983 (Box 15, Folder 13-17)
    - Stories -- Battler: 1961, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Stories -- Empty Closet, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Stories -- Islands, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Stories -- Nothing to Do But Lie Here and Come Apart, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Stories -- Sacred Fire / Air We Breathe, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Stories -- The Story, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Stories -- Untitled, 1968-1971 (Box 16, Folder 7-10)
  - Subseries I.B. Publications, 1966-2012, undated; 9 Linear Feet 14 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 1 oversize flat box; 4 audiocassettes
    Arranged in alphabetical order by title. The inventory lists an alphabetical range by title, grouped by publication size.
    These approximately 300 small and large circulation newspapers and magazines contain works by Lally which date primarily from the 1960s through the 1980s. Alternative press titles include All You Can Eat (1972), FagRag (1973), The Great Speckled Bird (1970-1971), and literary magazines Blue Suede Shoes (1971), L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E (1978-1980), and Buffalo Stamps (1972). Lally also contributed articles, editorials, reviews, letters, and poems to publications of a radical, political, counter-cultural and/or gay orientation including Campus Underground (1968–1969), Daily Rag (1973), Unicorn Times (circa 1974), Washington Review, (1979-1993, 2001), Washington Review of the Arts (1975-1977), and Woodwind(1972). Issues of Venice Magazine (1988, 1990, 1995) which Lally founded and edited are in this subseries. Black Box, a publication in audiocassette form and which Lally was editor for a time, can also be found in this subseries. The publication, Matchbook, which is 1-word poems contained within real matchbooks is in this subseries.
    - # -- Asphalt, 1969-1993 (Box 74, Folder 7-11)
    - B City -- Chouteau Review, 1970-1996, undated (Box 85, Folder 1-13)
    - Clown War -- Diana's Bimonthly, 1967-1980 (Box 86, Folder 1-8)
    - Dodgems -- Gargoyle, 1967-1997, undated (Box 87, Folder 1-10)
    - Gato -- Hanging Loose, 1966-1981 (Box 88, Folder 1-9)
    - Hey Lady -- Kaleidoscope, 1967-1997, undated (Box 89, Folder 1-14)
    - Kamadhenu -- Mag City, 1970-1994, undated (Box 90, Folder 1-10)
    - Margins -- The New Journal, 1969-1980, undated (Box 91, Folder 1-11)
    - New Letters -- The Poetry Project Newsletter, 1970-2012 (Box 92, Folder 1-12)
    - The Poetry Project Newsletter -- Shell, 1969-2012 (Box 93, Folder 1-12)
    - Shiny -- Sun and Moon, 1973-2000, undated (Box 94, Folder 1-10)
    - Thirst -- Voyages, 1969-2009, undated (Box 95, Folder 1-11)
    - Wake Up Heavy -- Zone One, 1974, 1977, 2001 (Box 96, Folder 1-4)
    - Hard Pressed -- Strange Faeces, 1970-1982 (Box 96, Folder 5-9)
    - Telephone -- The World, 1969-1977 (Box 97, Folder 1-5)
    - Apropos -- Venice Magazine, 1969-1995, undated (Box 79, Folder 6-11)
    - All You Can Eat -- Middle Earth, 1968-1997 (Box 80, Folder 5-13)
    - The New Patriot -- U.S. Farm News, 1969-1979, undated (Box 98, Folder 1-7)
    - Washington Review -- Woodwind, 1972, 1977-2001 (Box 99, Folder 1-3)
    - Black Box Audio Magazine, 1972, 1974 (Box 83)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      4 audiocassettes
  - Subseries I.C. Readings and Events, 1972-2012; 5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, 1 record carton, 1 oversize flat box, and 2 flat-file folders; 68 audiocassettes; 4 videocassettes (vhs); 7 Gigabytes in 27 computer, audio, and video files
    Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    This subseries contains material related to Michael Lally's performances as a poet, including poetry readings and recorded spoken albums. Contracts, publicity, posters, ephemera, reviews, and audiovisual and digital recordings of Lally's poetry readings and events date from the 1970s to the 2000s. Lally's Poetry in Motion series files contain publicity and planning material related to readings performed by a mix of Hollywood celebrities (Alec Baldwin, Robert Downey, Jr., and Ally Sheedy) and poets (Jack Grapes, Hubert Selby, Jr., and Wanda Coleman) in the 1980s and 1990s in while he was living in Los Angeles. See Series II.C. for correspondence files on this project. Electronic records in this subseries contain poetry reading albums and other event recordings, including Jazzspeak: A Word Collection, Michael Lally: Lost Angels, and Poets Against War. Digital images of a 2004 poetry reading and a digital video recording of a documentary on Hubert Selby, Jr. with a Lally interview are also in this subseries.
    - Album -- JazzSpeak: A Word Collection, 1991; cuid36269 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_361_ER_5)